## W. Ryan Livingston

Somerville, MA  $\diamond$  +1 330-717-2747  $\diamond$  wryanlivingston@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/w-ryan-livingston/

#### **SUMMARY**

A self-motivated software engineer returning to the workforce with 12 years of experience in technical computing as an individual contributor, manager, and product owner. Combines technical strength, a proven ability to learn new technology, a strong user focus, a demonstrated ability to deliver important projects, leadership, and excellent communication skills. Delivers software that is tested, maintainable, performant, documented, and of maximal utility.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### MathWorks - MATLAB Coder

May 2022 - September 2023

Software Engineering Manager

Natick, MA

- · Led a team of 4-6 engineers working on MATLAB Coder, a MATLAB to C/C++ source-to-source optimizing compiler
- $\cdot$  Team designed, enhanced, and developed core workflows, generation of multithreaded OpenMP parallel C/C++, compiler transforms, a multithreaded runtime library, static code checkers, command-line APIs, and GUI workflows for MATLAB users to convert their MATLAB code to deployable C/C++
- · Provided technical and career mentorship to team members and interns improving team and collaborator effectiveness
- · Acted as a technical point of contact on a broad multi-language (C/C++/MATLAB) codebase
- $\cdot$  Interfaced with other product teams to negotiate strategies and collaboration
- · Extensively worked with cross-functional teams including documentation, user experience (UX), quality engineering, marketing, project management, and senior management to design features and set direction
- · Met with customers and customer-facing engineers to understand product gaps, pains, and opportunities
- · Presented product plans and features at customer conferences to solicit feedback
- · Set product direction with a sibling team lead based on this feedback, company priorities, and product vision
- · Acted as a technical and directional point of contact for a remote development team in Bangalore, India
- · Led hiring and recruiting for the team and participated in interview teams for our other cross-functional teams

#### MathWorks - MATLAB Coder

October 2017 - May 2022

Senior Team Lead

Natick, MA

- · In addition to Software Engineering Manager responsibilities, contributed to development efforts by implementing new functionality and debugging and fixing bugs
- · Got company buy-in for and participated in the redesign of the main MATLAB Coder workflow GUI
- $\cdot$  Coordinated a multi-year project to remove 200k lines of Java from our codebase
- · Helped design the ability to call the FFTW library in the generated code and mentored implementing team
- · Used TypeScript to implement a Language Server Protocol (LSP) server for MATLAB to provide IDE-like functionality (e.g. code navigation, completions, etc.) while editing MATLAB code in Emacs, Visual Studio Code, Sublime, and Vim for hundreds of MathWorks engineers
- · Acted as an advisor to the team who shipped similar LSP support to customers

#### MathWorks - MATLAB Coder

July 2012 - October 2017

Software Engineer, Senior Software Engineer

Natick, MA

- · Participated in the full software development lifecycle including requirements specification, design, implementation in C++ and MATLAB, functional testing, performance testing, and user documentation
- $\cdot$  Added the ability for generated standalone C/C++ to call the high-performance libraries BLAS and LAPACK yielding speedups of up to 40%
- · Extended an LLVM-based JIT to call BLAS and LAPACK for relevant operations
- · Implemented support for MATLAB runtime library capabilities like file I/O and string processing to enable user workflows
- · Performed performance evaluation and performance optimization of the generated C/C++ code using VTune
- · Added support for 64-bit integers and extended enumeration types to MATLAB Coder
- · Designed and implemented the MATLAB Coder version of the MATLAB sparse matrix type
- · Led and mentored a team implementing sparse matrix algorithm support
- · Adapted random number generation to support multiple streams in generated OpenMP parallel code
- · Diligently authored functional and performance tests ensuring quality and efficiency in shipped code

- · Developed and deployed 2 web apps with JavaScript and a Python Flask RESTful API used by multiple teams
- · Implemented various editor enhancements and tools for Emacs and Visual Studio Code
- · Set up a CI/CD pipeline using Gitlab with a colleague to automatically build, test, and deploy internal tooling

MathWorks
July 2011 - July 2012
Application Support Engineer
Natick, MA

- · Provided technical support for users of MathWorks products in areas like code deployment, parallel computing, external language interfaces, and hardware interfaces via direct customer calls and emails while mentoring new technical support team members
- · Implemented software development projects:

Extended MATLAB TIFF reading and writing capabilities to support the BigTIFF file format (files larger than 4GB) Used the EDG C++ front end to gather info about classes, templates, and types from a user-provided C++ file

#### PERSONAL PROJECT

## FZF Fuzzy Quick Open Visual Studio Code Extension

https://github.com/rlivings39/vscode-fzf-quick-open

· A Visual Studio Code extension to integrate the searching speed and power of tools like fzf, fd, and ripgrep

### **EDUCATION**

# The University of Georgia Master of Arts in Mathematics

2009 - 2011

Athens, GA

- · Wrote programs to discover and test a finite solution set for a conjecture in an algebraic geometry research group
- · Taught precalculus and worked as a TA for upper-level undergrad math courses

## Youngstown State University

2005 - 2009

Bachelor of Science (BS) Mathematics and Computer Science

Youngstown, OH

- · Presented at national undergraduate conferences as a member of Pi Mu Epsilon
- · Worked as a MATLAB programmer and tutored in the undergraduate math center

## SKILLS

Programming Languages
Frameworks And Tools
Testing
Some Exposure To

C, C++, Python, MATLAB, JavaScript, TypeScript
Visual Studio Code, Emacs, bash, gcc, clang, gdb, Git, Perforce, VTune
xUnit, Google Test, performance testing
RESTful APIs w/ Flask, Docker